Matthew K. Perez

Email: mkperez@umich.edu | Phone: (808) 286-4393 Website: https://matthewkperez.com/

RESEARCH INTEREST

My research interests center around leveraging the rich signal of human speech for characterizing health, behavior, and mood using machine learning models. My research has touched on various topics, including automatic speech recognition, speech synthesis, acoustic feature analysis, and computational paralinguistics. My thesis work largely involves developing novel approaches to enable individuals with speech impairments to communicate effectively, which has driven my passion for advancing the field of speech technology to benefit a broader range of populations.

EDUC.

EDUCATION	
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor	2017 – 2023 (<i>expected</i>)
Ph.D. in Computer Science and Engineering	
Advisor: Dr. Emily Mower Provost	
University of Michigan, Ann Arbor	2017 - 2019
M.S. in Computer Science and Engineering	
University of Notre Dame	2013 - 2017
B.S. in Computer Science, Cum Laude	
AWARDS	
NSF Graduate Research Fellowship (GRFP)	2020 - 2023
GEM Ph.D. Engineering Fellowship	2019 - 2020
Dean's List, University of Notre Dame	2015 - 2017
Balfour-Hesburgh Scholar, University of Notre Dame	2013 - 2017

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

Computational Human Artificial Intelligence (CHAI) Lab	2017 – Present
University of Michigan	Ann Arbor, MI
TTT 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1 1	 11.1

Working on speech and signal processing methods for analyzing various neurological conditions.

Research Assistant: Mobile Computing Lab

University of Notre Dame

2015-2016 Notre Dame, IN

Investigated speech analysis methods for classifying mild traumatic brain injuries (concussions).

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Research Intern (Speech Synthesis Team)

2022

Google

Mountain View, CA

Worked on fine-tuning large, self-supervised speech models for end-to-end pronunciation modeling. I found that multilingual training can be leveraged to improve model performance across multiple languages with significant performance improvements for low-resource languages.

Research Intern (Speech/Signals Team)

2021

Cogito Corporation

Virtual

Researched novel approaches for multimodal fusion in large transformer-based models for speech emotion recognition. This work showed that modeling paralinguistic events such as silence within a large language model (BERT) can lead to improved emotion recognition performance.

Research Intern (Bioengineering Tech Systems Group)

2019

MIT Lincoln Laboratory

Lexington, MA

Researched speech-based articulation features for identifying neurological conditions such as depression.

Software Engineer Intern (*iOS team*)

2016

Garmin

Olathe, KS

Contributed to the development of the Garmin iOS application, which syncs wearable device data to/from the iPhone. Specifically, implemented *Today Extensions* for the Garmin Connect Mobile app, which displays wearable health information like steps, activities, etc. I presented work to research teams and company executives.

PUBLICATIONS

Yang Yu, **Matthew Perez**, Ankur Bapna, Fadi Haik, Siamak Tazari, Yu Zhang. "PronScribe: Highly accurate multimodal phonemic transcription from speech and text". Interspeech 2023 (In submission)

James Tavernor, **Matthew Perez**, Emily Mower Provost. "Episodic Memory For Domain-Adaptable, Robust Speech Emotion Recognition". Interspeech 2023 (In submission)

Matthew Perez, Mimansa Jaiswal, Minx Niu, Cristina Gorrostieta, Matthew Roddy, Kye Taylor, Reza Lotfian, John Kane, Emily Mower Provost. "Mind the gap: On the value of silence representations to lexical-based speech emotion recognition". Interspeech 2022. (poster presentation)

Amrit Romana, Minxue Niu, **Matthew Perez**, Angela Roberts, Emily Mower Provost. "Enabling Off-the-Shelf Disfluency Detection and Categorization for Pathological Speech". Interspeech 2022. (oral *presentation*)

Matthew Perez, Amrit Romana, Noelle Carlozzi, Praveen Dayalu, Jennifer Ann Miner, Angela Roberts, and Emily Mower Provost. "Articulatory Coordination for Speech Motor Tracking in Huntington Disease" Interspeech 2021. (*oral presentation*)

Amrit Romana, John Bandon, **Matthew Perez**, Stephanie Gutierrez, Richard Richter, Angela Roberts, Emily Mower Provost. "Automatically Detecting Errors and Disfluencies in Read Speech to Predict Cognitive Impairment in People with Parkinson's Disease". Interspeech 2021 (oral presentation)

Zakaria Aldeneh, **Matthew Perez**, and Emily Mower Provost. "Learning Paralinguistic Features from Audiobooks through Style Voice Conversion" NAACL 2021. (*virtual presentation*)

Matthew Perez, Zakaria Aldeneh, and Emily Mower Provost. "Aphasic Speech Recognition using a Mixture of Speech Intelligibility Experts" Interspeech 2020. (*virtual presentation*)

Matthew Perez, Wenyu Jin, Duc Le, Noelle Carlozzi, Praveen Dayalu, Angela Roberts, and Emily Mower Provost. "Classification of Huntington's Disease Using Acoustic and Lexical Features." Interspeech 2018. (*oral presentation*)

Louis Daudet, Nikhil Yadav, **Matthew Perez**, Christian Poellabauer, Sandra Schneider, Alan Huebner. "Portable mTBI Assessment Using Temporal and Frequency Analysis of Speech." IEEE Journal of Biomedical and Health Informatics 2017.

TALKS

Google-Speech Reading Group, Mountain View	2022
The National GEM Consortium Technical Workshop, Virtual	2020
Graduate Engineering Research Symposium, Ann Arbor (Student Poster Award)	2018

SERVICES

Reviewer, Transactions on Audio, Speech and Language Processing	2023
Reviewer, Transactions of Affective Computing	2023
Reviewer, Affective Computing & Intelligent Interaction (ACII)	2021
Reviewer, Computer Speech & Language	2020
Poster Chair, Michigan AI Symposium	2019

SKILLS

Languages: Python, Bash, C++, Objective-C

Software Frameworks: Kaldi, Speechbrain, Pytorch-kaldi, OpenSmile, Librosa, NumPy, Pandas

Machine Learning: Pytorch, Tensorflow, Keras, scikit-learn